Preliminary Guide to the Columbian College Office of the Dean records 1873-1990 RG0068
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Columbian College Office of the Dean records
1873-1990
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Columbian College of Arts and Sciences
RG0068
11.5 Linear Feet
Materials in this collection include academic guides for entering freshmen/students, original charter of Phi Beta Kappa at GW, photographs, committee on publications minutes, correspondence, Hatchet constitution, materials from the curriculum committee relating to the reform of the general education requirements for Columbian College, flags, committee on sponsored research, theses from Columbian College (including 1917 notebook on airplanes and military airplanes). The collections covers the years 1873 to 1993.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition data is unknown.
Historical or Biographical Note
The George Washington University began in 1821 as The Columbian College. The College's origins can be traced to George Washington, who long argued for the creation of a university within the District of Columbia. In furtherance of that cause, Washington bequeathed 50 shares of The Potomac Company "towards the endowment of a University to be established within the limits of the District of Columbia, under the auspices of the General Government, if that government should incline to extend a fostering hand towards it." Due to congressional inaction, however, Washington's bequest was never utilized.
Aware of Washington's hopes and desirous of fostering education among missionaries and the clergy, a group of ministers and laymen raised funds for the purchase of a site for the College and petitioned Congress for a charter. The Congressional charter was approved by President Monroe on February 9, 1821 and The Columbian College was created. The name of the College was changed in 1873 to Columbian University and in 1904 to The George Washington University.
Since its founding, Columbian College, the University's original college of liberal arts and sciences, has been the cornerstone of the campus community. Its first bachelors degree was awarded in 1824, with the first Master of Arts degree following in 1831. The University awarded its first Doctor of Philosophy degree in 1888, one of the first institutions in the United States to do so.
This note was written in 2005.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include academic guides for entering freshmen/students, original charter of Phi Beta Kappa at GW, photographs, committee on publications minutes, correspondence, Hatchet constitution, materials from the curriculum committee relating to the reform of the general education requirements for Columbian College, flags, committee on sponsored research, theses from Columbian College (including 1917 notebook on airplanes and military airplanes). The collections covers the years 1873 to 1993.
Collection Organization
Organized into nine series: Sponsored research, Flags, Academic guide, Theses, Phi Beta Kappa, Curriculum committee, Committee on individual programs, Committee on publications, and Office files.
Phi Beta Kappa; Dissertations, Academic; Research; Photographs; Committees; Publications; Education; Students
- Sponsored research, 1969; RG0068 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of materials elated to the committee on sponsored research. The materials date from 1969.
  Formerly ACC#88
  This series has a paper container list in the reading room, please ask staff for assistance.
  - Committee on Sponsored Research, 03/25/1969-07/18/1990; RG0068 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Sponsored Research, 1968-1969; RG0068 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Sponsored Research, 1969; RG0068 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Flags, RG0068 Series 2 (Box 1, Box 2)
  This series consists of two flags for the Columbian College and Graduate School of Arts and Sciences. The materials have no ascertainable date.
  Formerly ACC#312
- Academic guide, 1965-1990; RG0068 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1, Box SHARED 2)
  This series consists of academic guide for entering freshmen/students. The materials range in date from 1965-90.
  Formerly ACC#388
  - Academic Guide for Entering Freshmen, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    2 copies
  - Academic Guide for Entering Freshmen, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Freshmen, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Freshmen, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Freshmen, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Freshmen, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Freshmen, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Freshmen, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Academic Guide for Entering Students, 1980, 1983, 1984; Series 3 (Box SHARED 2, Folder 9)
- Theses, 1963-1967; RG0068 Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of ten theses from Columbian College mostly regarding national defense (including c.1917 notebook on airplanes and military airplanes), The materials range in date from 1963-67.
  Formerly ACC#446
  This series has a container list in electronic form, please ask staff for assistance.
- Phi Beta Kappa, ca.1938; RG0068 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of original charter of Phi Beta Kappa at GW, Feb. 22, 1938; two framed photos of faculty members, The materials range in date from ca.1938.
  Formerly ACC#1018
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Copies of two letters dealing with the acquisition of the items for the university archives: one from Dean Linton and the other from university archivist Sharon Galperin.
  - Photo of faculty members, 1938 ca. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    List of faculty, seated left to right: Florence Mears, Wood Gray, George Neeley Henning, Nenry Grattan Doyle; standing left to right: Leland W. Parr, Raymond J. Seeger, Richard N. Owens, Lowell Ragatz, Robert Whitney Bolwell
  - Photo of charter faculty members of the GWU chapter of Phi Beta Kappa., 1938 ca. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    List of faculty, seated left to right: Prof. George M. Churchill, Prof. Spencer Gordon, Dr. Wilson Compton, Trustee Charles R. Mann, Prof. Charles S. Collier, Associate Prof. Wood Gray, Associate Prof. Florence Mears, Dean Henry Grattan Doyle, Prof. George N. Henning, Prof. Cloyd H. Marvin, Prof. Lowell J. Ragatz, Provost William C. Ruediger, Trustee Charles W. Gerstenberg, Dr. Harry Garfield, Trustee Gilbert Grosvenor, Miss. Edith Mortensen, Dr. Zigmond Meyer Lebansohn, Dean Robert W. Bolwell; standing left to right: Prof. William A. Wilbur, Dr. John Harold Hanks, Prof. Richard N. Owens, Dr. William Webster Diehl, Assistant Prof. Ira B. Hansen, Mr. Douglas Wilson, Dr. Howard M. Merriman, Dr. Nathanael Howard Engle, Prof. Errett C. Albritton, Dr. Walter Kendall Myers, Dr. Mabel Harlakenden Grosvenor, Dr. Charles Robert Less Halley, Prof. Colin M. Mackall, Prof. Edward H. Sehrt, Assistant Prof. George W. Stone, Jr., Mr. Robert W. Gordon, Prof. James H. Taylor, Associate Prof. Leland W. Parr, Prof. Robert F. Griggs, Associate Prof. Raymond J. Seeger.
  - Phi Beta Kappa Charter, 02/22/1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Curriculum committee, 1985-1987; RG0068 Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of materials from the curriculum committee related to the reform of general education requirements for Columbian College, The materials range in date from 1985-87.
  Formerly RG9; formerly ACC#984
  This series is unprocessed, please ask staff for assistance.
- Committee on individual programs, 1975-1981; RG0068 Series 7; 3.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of program files of students in M.A./M.S. program. The materials range in date from 1975-81.
  Formerly RG10.9; formerly ACC#141
- Committee on publications, 1946-1951; RG0068 Series 8; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of committee on publications materials, including minutes, correspondence, Hatchet constitution, Cherry Tree. The materials range in date from 1946-51.
  Formerly ACC#909
  - Minutes of the Committee on Publications, 09/01/1945-08/31/1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Publications - controversy with student newspaper "Hatchet", 09/01/1946-08/31/1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Publications - "Surveyor", 09/01/1947-08/31/1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Publications - "Cherry Tree" yearbook, 09/01/1947-08/31/1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Publications - "Hatchet" constitution and correspondence, 09/01/1947-08/31/1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Publications - "Hatchet" correspondence with other universities regarding constitution, 09/01/1947-08/31/1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Publications - "Hatchet" staff resumes and correspondence, 09/01/1947-08/31/1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Committee on Publications - correspondence, 09/01/1947-08/31/1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Publications - "Cherry Tree" yearbook, 09/01/1948-08/31/1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Publications - "Speculum" medical school yearbook, 09/01/1948-08/31/1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Publications - "The Colonial Review" yearbook, 09/01/1948-08/31/1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Publications - "Hatchet", 09/01/1948-08/31/1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Committee on Publications, 09/01/1948-08/31/1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Committee on Publications - "The Colonial Review", 09/01/1949-08/31/1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Committee on Publications, 09/01/1949-08/31/1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Committee on Publications - "Cherry Tree", 09/01/1949-08/31/1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Committee on Publications, 09/01/1950-08/31/1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Committee on Publications - "The Colonial Review", 09/01/1950-08/31/1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Committee on Publications - "Hatchet" staff qualifications and correspondence, satirical copy of "Tomahawk" from April Fool's Day, 09/01/1950-08/31/1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Office files, 1873-1974; RG0068 Series 9; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of an application, a catalogue, reports, correspondence, and event programs. They range in date from 1873 to 1974. They concern the Isaac Davis Award in Public Speaking, the Columbian University School of Graduate Studies, "The Development and Functions of the Graduate School", the founding of the Graduate studies at Columbian University, "Plan of the Columbian University", the history graduate program, lectures, and doctoral disputation.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Architecture Department, 1913-1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Department, 1943-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Department - Courses, 1963 ca.-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Art Department - Art at the Columbian College, 1840-1865, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Art Department - Publication - "The Museum and the Art Teacher," 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Awards and Prizes - Isaac Davis Award in Public Speaking, 1919-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Colgate University - Degrees Conferred by Columbian College 1844, 1832-1859 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Colgate University - Transcripts of Records and Correspondence Relating to Columbian College (Notes made July 14-19, 1964.), 1964 ca. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912-2005), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912- ) - Academic Advising, 1912-1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912- ) - Academic Programs, 1952-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912- ) - Committees - Academic Survey Committee (1963-1965) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912- ) - Committees - Committee on Grades (1968-1969) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912- ) - Dean's Office, 1981-2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912- ) - Degree Requirements, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912- ) - Grading, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (1912- ) - Liberal Arts Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences - Peer Advising, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences, School of - Pre-Medical Courses, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School - Catalog, 1881-1882 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Columbain College Preparatory School Catalog, 1883-1884 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1884-1885 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1885-1886 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1886-1887 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1887-1888 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1889-1890 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School Catalog, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School - Catalog - 1896-1897 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School (1821-1897) - Commencement Programs, 1867-1947 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School (1821-1897) - Faculty - Richards, Zalmon, (1849-1851), 1966-1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School (1821-1897) - History, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School, (1821-1897) - Library Holdings (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Columbian College Preparatory School (1821-1897) - Students - Bell, William D., 2/8/1940-6/27/1940 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Columbian Institute, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Columbian University - Department of Public Health, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Columbian Univeristy - Meteorology Courses (Professor Cleveland Abbe), undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Columbian University- Ordinance Providing for the Conduct of the Departments of Medicine and Dentistry and the University Hospital, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Community Service - Campus Community Service, 1992, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Corcoran School of Science and Arts (1884-1903), 1873-1904 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Degrees, Doctoral - Recipients, 1894-1930 Biographical Information A-I (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Degrees, Doctoral - Recipients, 1894-1930 Biographical Information, J-Z (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Degrees - History, 1940 ca.-1990 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Degrees - History - Ph.D. Program, 1946-1988 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Doctoral Dissertations (1894- ), 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Doctoral Programs at GW since World War II, 3/1930-1988 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - East Asian Art History Program (1981- ), 11/4/1981 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - East Asian Language and Literature Department, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Economics Department, 1966-1980 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Far Eastern Studies, 1968-1976 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Film Studies, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Foreign Language Study, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Forensic Science, Department of, 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Geography Department, 1949-1998 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Geology Department, 1966-1990 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Germanic Languages and Literatures, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Graduate School 1865-1900, 1894-9 /28/1899 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Graduate Studies - Doctoral Disputations 1894-1918, 6/5/1894-5/20/1918 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Graduate Studies, School of 1894-1903, 1892-1903 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Graduate Studies, School of - History, 1895-1967 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - History of GW 1851-1900, 4/25/1873-1860 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Columbian College of Arts and Sciences' Float for President Barack Obama's Inaugural Parade, September 2008-20 January 2009; Piece of the Columbian College of Arts and Sciences' float for President Barack Obama's Inaugural Parade. Multi-colored painted canvas, approximately 7 ft. x 8 ft., with lioness and cub from the CCAS and music notation for GW's Alma Mater. Canvas stretched on wooden frame. (Object 1)
  Obama, Barack, President